Shinonome Institute
Nano!
（はかせ）なの！
なの？
Nano?
Nano~
なーのー！
Nano!
なの
Yes?
（東雲(しののめ)なの）はあい
Nano, Nano!
（はかせ）なの なの！
Yes?
はあい ウフフッ
Nano!
（はかせ）なのっ
Yes, yes.
（なの）はあい はい
It's Nyan~
Nano!
なの！
Look, look!
（はかせ）見て 見て！
It's Professor, nyan~!
はかせだにゃん
Nyan.
（はかせ）にゃあ
（なの）ああ
（はかせ）阪本(さかもと)も見て見て
はかせだにゃん
You too, Sakamoto... Look, look!
It's Professor, nyan~!
はっかせだにゃあ
Professor.
（なの）はかせ
That's probably... moe!
それは 多分“萌(も)え”です！
Nyan~?
にゃあ
Nyan~!
It's Professor, nyan~!
はっかせだにゃん
It's moe!
（なの）萌えです
It's Professor, nyan~!
はっかせだにゃあ
It's moe!
（なの）萌えです
It's Professor, nyan~!
（はかせ）はっかせだにゃーん
It's moe!
（なの）萌えです
（阪本）ふうん
It's Professor, nyan nyan~!
（はかせ）
はっかせだにゃん にゃん
It's moe!
（なの）萌えでーす
（はかせ）はっかせだにゃん
It's Professor, nyan~!
（なの）萌えです
It's moe!
It's Professor, nyan nyan~!
（はかせ）
はっかせだにゃん にゃん
（ナレーター）
東雲家は 今日も平和であった
The Shinonome household was at peace again today.
Why is the Earth round?
（中之条 剛(なかのじょうつよし)）
地球が なぜ丸いのか？
ロケットが なぜ飛べるのか？
Why do rockets fly?
Why do magnets pull toward each other?
なぜ 磁石が引き合うのか？
Everything in this world can be proven by science.
この世のものは すべて
科学で証明できるんだ
Grave
In this world, there are talks about the afterworld,
世間で取り沙汰される死後の世界や
幽霊や怪談などの心霊現象
ghosts, ghost stories and other spiritual phenomena.
There's no way those kinds of sleep-inducing things could be real!
そんな眠たい たぐいのものは
あるはずがない！
Grave
It'd be bad if they were...
あっては いけないんだ
In other words...
Mt. Osore
つまり―
I don't believe in spiritualists!
イタコが 信じられないんだ！
Nichijou 19
Using my day off, I spent 8 hours going one-way to Mt. Osore.
僕は 休日を利用し
片道８時間の恐山(おそれざん)の地に立った
Getting closer to the summit, the beating of my heart increases.
山頂に近づくにつれ
胸の鼓動が加速する
I wonder if a spiritualist really exists here.
本当にイタコはいるのか？
いるとしたら どこに？
If so, where?
１人で こんなところに
住んでいるのだろうか？
I wonder if she would live alone here.
Or...
それとも…
Spiritualist
There she is!
（中之条）いた！
Spiritualist
A-All right!
（中之条）よ… よし！
早速 呼んでもらおうじゃないか
Let's have her summon something already.
Excuse me.
（中之条）すみません
（イタコ）はい
Yes.
Um... Please summon some soap!
（中之条）あの
せっけんを呼んでください！
Ah, okay.
あっ はい
Bubble, it's Soap!
どうも せっけんでーすっ
（イタコ）
あーあー あーあー
マイクテス マイクテス ツイ
Mic test... mic test... mic test, test, test.
マイクテス テステス ツイー
ツイ ツイ ツイー
What's this sensation of helplessness?
なんだ？ この
どうしようもない感覚は…
Could it be there's someone called Soap...?
（中之条）
もしかしたら“せっけん”と
いう人がいるの かも
マイクテス テス ツイー ツイー
ツイ シー シッハッ ハッ
I-It's S-Soap.
せっ せ せっけん せっけん
せっけん せっけんデス デス
No, there can't be.
（中之条）
いや ひるんじゃダメだ
What if I keep asking... Eventually, a contradiction point will appear.
なに 質問していけば
いずれ矛盾点が出てくるさ
I have a question.
質問です
What's the blood type of Soap?
せっけんの血液型は
何型ですか？
（イタコ）んん？ さあ
Who knows?
Let's try a simpler person.
（中之条）もっと
分かりやすい人物にしよう
Excuse me.
（中之条）すみません
Nobunaga... Please summon Oda Nobunaga!
信長(のぶなが)を… 織田(おだ)信長を
呼んでください
Please give me a break.
勘弁してください
Rejecting me before even trying to summon him?
（中之条）
呼ぶ 呼ばないの前に拒否とは
No, she's old after all.
いやあ なにぶん お年寄りだ
体調の面もあるのだろう
She has to look after her health.
I shouldn't scold her here.
ここで責めるのは…
イヤーッ！
Excuse me.
失礼します
Let's go home.
（中之条）帰ろう
僕には 人は責められない
Scolding people is not for me.
Just by knowing that, I should reap what I've sown.
それが分かっただけでも
収穫と しようじゃないか
Oh, Onii-san?
あっ お兄さーん
（中之条）はっ
（イタコ）5,000円になります
That'll be 5000 yen.
Daruma Otoshi
100 Points
Sneezing
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）ほっ おっ
No way!
...of men.
Nichijou 20
2nd Period
Self Study
（祐子）じゃあ いくよ
Okay, here goes.
Rock, paper, scissors.
じゃんけん　ぽん
キャア！
W-Whoa!
わっ わっ わあーお！
You got it wrong, Mai-chan! Didn't I just explain it?
違うよ 麻衣(まい)ちゃん
さっき説明したじゃんか
勝ったら たたくんだよ
You have to hit me if you win!
It's amazing. You've got incredible concentration.
すごいよ　すごい仕打ちだよ
ある意味 たたくより ひどいよ
In a way, it's even crueller than hitting me.
いい？ さっき説明したとおり―
Listen.
As I've just explained,
when you lose, you defend. When you win, you hit. Okay?
負けたら防御
勝ったら たたくんだからね
今じゃねえよ
なんで 今 殴ったの？
Not now! Why did you hit me now?!
Because I won just then.
（水上(みなかみ)麻衣）
いや さっき勝ったから
It wasn't now, was it? It was just then!
今じゃないでしょ さっきじゃん
It's the moment!
瞬間だよ 瞬間に生きてるんだよ
Live for the moment!
We're that kind of living thing, you know!
First comes rock, next comes paper. Rockscispaper doesn't count,
rock, paper, scissors!
私たちは
そういう生き物なんだよ！
It's Nano, nyan~
Okay then, let's do it again.
そいじゃあ まあ
仕切り直していくよ
Rock, paper, scissors.
じゃんけん
ぽん
You have zero motivation to play?!
（祐子）やる気ゼロかよっ
You are a clown!
ピエロだよ　とんだピエロだよ
How much of a clown can you be?!
Something is coming... mentally.
（祐子）
精神的に くるものあるよ
Ah, hold on, Mai-chan.
ああっ ちょっと 麻衣ちゃん？
あった
There it is.
Mai-chan, w-what's with that?
（祐子）麻衣ちゃん
それ ど… どうしたの？
I carved it.
彫った
Thank god!
（祐子）
よかったあ　生まれ変わって
出てきたのかと思ったあ
I thought it had been reincarnated!
I will put this here.
（麻衣）
これを ここに　フッフフ
Somehow, she looks really happy.
（祐子）なんか
すごい うれしそうだ
Ah, well, that doesn't matter. Let's start.
まあ そんなん
どうでもいいから やるよ
はい　じゃんけん
Okay. Rock, paper, scissors.
ぽん
M-Mai-chan.
ま… 麻衣ちゃん　それ
That's...
...rockscispaper...!
（祐子）
グッチョパじゃーんっ
No way... such a brutal...
そんな 殺生な ううっ
Seriously, Mai-chan, that doesn't count.
もう 麻衣ちゃん！
なしだよ なし　グッチョパなし！
あと 仏でたたくのもなし！
Rockscispaper doesn't count.
Also, hitting with the Buddha doesn't count either.
Okay, let's do it again.
じゃあ いくよ　最初は グー
First comes rock-
Rock, paper, scissors.
じゃんけん
ぽん
ああ　麻衣ちゃん
Mai-chan...
That, that!
それそれ それだよ 麻衣ちゃん
もう やればできるじゃーん
That's it Mai-chan.
See, you can do it if you try!
Okay, let's do the next one.
よし　次やろう 次
First comes rock-
えーと 最初は―
グウウ！
God is dead!
（祐子）God is DEAD
God has died.
（ナレーター）神は死んだ！
（祐子）うう…
ちょっと なんで殴んの？
Hey, why did you hit me?!
You did it properly just now!
もう さっきは
ちゃんと できたじゃーん
（麻衣）うーん
何というか やりたくないから
How do I say it... Because I don't want to play.
Can I take a look at your Maitreya?
弥勒菩薩(みろくぼさつ) 見ていい？
Sure.
（麻衣）いいよ
（なの）じゃあ 図書館に
本 返しに行ってきまーす
Shinonome Institute
Then, I'll be going to the library to return the books!
ちゃーんと お留守番してて
くださいねえ
Shinonome Institute
（はかせ）はーい
Make sure you look after the house, okay?
（なの）フウ
Yes!
Nichijou 21
You can't have too much
ice cream and juice!
I wonder why Nano's daruma has only one eye...
どうして なのの だるまは
目が１個しかないんだろう？
That's it!
If Professor gave it another eye, Professor might get praised!
そうだ　はかせが
ちゃんとした目にすれば―
Or perhaps...
...Nano may say "it's okay to eat as many snacks as you like"!
褒められちゃかもしれない
もしかしたら なのは―
“お菓子 いっぱい
食べていいよ”って―
言うかもしれない
ちょっと
間違っちゃったかもしれない
I might've got it a little bit wrong...
It's Nano's, so what do I do...
なのの なのに どうしよう
Oh!
ハッ　もしかしたら
怒られるかもしれない
She might get mad at me!
You won't get any snacks for a long time!
（なの）
はかせは 当分おやつ抜きです！
Um... here... and here...
えっと こうして こうして…
うーん　うぐう
What are you doing?
（阪本）何してんだ？
S-Sakamoto, what should I do? This...
あっ 阪本　どうしよう これ
What is this?
（阪本）何だ？ こりゃ
お前　何やってんだ！
What were you doing?!
This is hers, right?
これ 娘のだろ？
You see, it didn't have an eye...
だって 目がなかったから
It can't be helped, try doing what I say.
しょうがねえなあ
俺の言うとおりにしてみ
（はかせ）ブッハハハハッ
（阪本）ハハハハッ
（はかせ）ウヒヒ ヒイヒイッ
（阪本）ハッ ヨッ アハハハッ
（はかせ）ハーッ ハッ ハーッ
（阪本）ヒッ ヒイッ ヒーッ
I'm home!
（なの）ただいま！
Stay in good health.
（阪本）達者でな
Ah, Sakamoto!
（はかせ）あっ 阪本
Ah, Sakamoto-san, you're going out?
（なの）あっ あれ？
阪本さん　お出かけですか？
Professor, I'm home.
はかせ　ただいま
I'm late because it took me some time to choose some new books to borrow.
新しく借りてくる本 選んでたら
遅くなっちゃいました
What are you doing?
何してるんですか？
Eh, what's with that stomach of yours?
…って はかせ
どうしたんです？ そのおなか
イヒッ ヒヒヒヒヒ エヘッ
It's not "Ehehe"!
（なの）エヘヘじゃなくて
うっ うんっ  う… 生まれる！
I-It'll be born!
（なの）ガーンッ
No, no, no, that's not possible.
…って いやいやいや
そんなわけ
ないじゃないですかあ
It'll be born!
生まれるの！
Um, is this some kind of game?
えっと
It'll be born!
何かの遊びですか？
No, it's not!
違うの なのの弟が生まれるの！
Nano's little brother is about to be born!
（なの）アハハハ ウフフ
It's your little brother.
弟です
オギャーッ オギャーッ
T-This isn't good.
（阪本）ダ… ダメだ こりゃ
（ねずみ）チュー
Kokkuri-san
Mio-chan, Mio-chan!
（祐子）
みおちゃん みおちゃん
What is it?
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）何？
Let's play Kokkuri-san!
こっくりさん やろう
Hm? What's that?
（みお）んん？ 何？ それ
（祐子）わっ わあ
みおちゃん　知らないんだ
Oh, you don't know it?
知んない
I don't.
Okay, I'll briefly explain it then.
（祐子）
んじゃ 軽く説明するね
First, you need to prepare a piece of paper by drawing a gate in the middle like this,
まず こうやって
真ん中に鳥居を描いて―
“はい”と“いいえ”と
五十音とを書いた紙を用意するのね
then you write "yes", "no" and the 50 characters of the Japanese syllabary on the page.
Mm.
Although in some regions, you're supposed to draw a fried tofu on the paper instead...
地域によっては 紙には―
油揚げを書いたほうがいいとか
いうのもあるんだけど
For now, let's just keep it simple.
今は 一番 簡単なのにしとくね
Mm.
（祐子）…で こっくりさんが
入ってこれるように―
Then, for Kokkuri-san to be able to come in,
you open the north-facing window.
北の窓を開けてっと
（みお）フム
Mm.
Then you set this 10-yen coin on the gate.
（祐子）それで この十円玉を
この鳥居の所にセットして―
We put both of our fingers on it and ask a question that you want to know about,
２人一緒に指を置いて
聞きたいことを質問するの
such as a person's secret, or who someone likes, or something that's bothering you.
人の秘密とか 好きな人のこととか
悩んでることとか
Mm.
If you do that, the 10-yen coin will move all by itself
and Kokkuri-san will answer your question.
そうすると
何もしてないのに―
十円玉がスーッと動いて
こっくりさんが答えてくれるんだよ
へえ
Isn't it amazing?
ねえ すごいでしょ？
でも タブーがあって
まず１人でやっちゃダメなのと―
There are some taboos, though.
First, don't do it by yourself.
Second, don't mess around when doing it,
ふざけてやっちゃダメ
低級霊に ひょう依されるから
or else you will be haunted by spirits...
（みお）ほう
Also, if you stop halfway through, you will be haunted, so be wary.
あと 途中で やめたりしても
ひょう依されちゃうから注意して
I see.
なるほど
It's something like that.
…て感じで 結構
危ない遊びなんだけどね
It's a pretty dangerous game, don't you think?
Anyway, why don't you give it a try?
まっ とりあえず
やってみようか
It's okay.
（みお）べつに いいよ
What?
（祐子）あーれー？
ええいっ
Nichijou 22
（桜井(さくらい)先生）ええと それでは―
Um... well, that's all for today.
今日は これで終わりにします
Tomorrow we have a mini-test, so everyone please study for it.
あしたは豆テストをしますので
皆さん　勉強してきてくださいね
Eh? Postpone it, postpone it!
（千代田(ちよだ)）ええ？ 延期 延期！
Wouldn't the outcome be exactly the same for you no matter how long it's postponed?
（片品(かたしな)）
おめえは いくら延期しても
結果は同じだろ？
（千代田）てへっ
（千代田）キャハハハハッ
（片品）ヒヒヒヒヒッ
Mini-test
English
（千代田）かもな
Probably.
Sakurai-sensei.
（祐子）桜井先生
（桜井）ああ
相生さん　何でしょうか？
What is it, Aioi-san?
There's something I want to ask you.
ちょっと 聞きたいことが
あるんですけど
あっ はい
Yes?
Um... about the test we had before.
えーと この前やった
テストなんですけど
What is this?
これ 何ですか？
Um... That's a fly.
（桜井）
えーと それは“fly(フライ)”ですね
No, not the answer.
（祐子）
ああ いや 答えじゃなくて―
I'm talking about this thing that looks like it'd vanish
pretty easily. Did you draw it, Sensei?
この ニフラムで消えそうなの
先生が書いたんですか？
Yes. I thought that if I included some
pictures, the test might be a little easier...
ああ はい
絵 入れたほうが―
テストが柔らかくなるかなあって
思いまして
You draw very interesting pictures, Sensei.
（祐子）先生って
面白い絵 描くんですね
I'm sorry.
すみません　私 絵ヘタだから
分かりにくかったですよね
I'm bad at drawing, so it was hard to understand wasn't it?
（祐子）へえ
（祐子）あっ そうだ
（桜井）えっ？
Ah! That's right.
Could you include a picture that I've drawn next time?
じゃあ 先生　今度 私の描いた絵
載せてくださいよ
I'll draw something really cool!
超カッコいいの描きますから
Okay.
ウフッ　はい
Ah, Mio-chan!
（祐子）あっ みおちゃん！
（みお）ん？
Listen, listen.
聞いて 聞いて
私の絵がテストに載るんだよ
My picture's going to be in the test.
Eh? Why?
（みお）えっ なんで？
Sensei said she'll put them in.
（祐子）
先生が載せてくれるって
If you draw something right now,
she'll definitely put yours in, maybe.
みおちゃんも 今 描けば
もれなく載るかもしれないよ
It's "definitely", but it's still "maybe"?
もれなくなのに
もれる可能性があるのかあ
Uh... you're not going to draw something?
あれ？ 描かないの？
No, I'm fine.
（みお）ああ
私は いいや　遠慮しとくよ
I'll pass on that.
Besides, I have to return this.
これ 返さないといけないし
Oh, really?
（祐子）ありゃ そう？
All right!
よーし　じゃ
カッコいい男を一筆
One cool guy-
（祐子）
♪ ちょいちょい ちょちょちょ
ちょこ ちょいちょい
フンフン
こんな感じですかねっと
Something like this?
（みお）だはは
Uwah! He's so cool!
うわあ カッコいいですねえ
（みお）どええ！
Aioi-san, you're so good at drawing.
相生さん　絵上手なんですね
尊敬です
You have my respect.
No, I'm not that good... I'm awesome at it!
いやあ それほどでも
あるよ！ なんつって ハハハッ
Just kidding.
Incidentally, his name is Samidare George.
ちなみに 名前は
五月雨(さみだれ)ジョージだったりします
（桜井）うわあ　ますます
カッコいいですねえ
That's even cooler.
（みお）ううっ　カッコいい？
Cool?!
Hold on a second you two.
ちょっと待って ２人とも
普通カッコいいっていうのは…
Normally, what you'd call cool is...
Piss off
...something like this, right?
（みお）こうでしょ！
（男）うっとうしい
Piss off!
Uwah! Amazing!
うわあ すごーい
アンガみたいですよ
It's just like a manga.
長野原さん
マンガとか描いてるんですか？
Naganohara-san, do you draw manga or something?
No- Well, only a little.
（みお）
いやあ まあ 少しだけ
Amazing!
（桜井）すごーい
今度 見せてください
Please show me next time.
That is, well...
（みお）あっ それは ちょっと
Eh? You can't?
（桜井）ええ ダメですか？
見たいです　見せてください
I want to see it.
Please show it to me.
Eh... Ah... But...
（みお）ええ ああ でも…
（祐子）んっ うんん
Give that back to me!
ちょっと貸して！
Mine are much cooler.
私のほうが
もっとカッコいいよ
（祐子）
♪ フンフン フフフ フフン
You just ripped off mine!
パクってるじゃん！
I didn't rip it off.
パクってないよ
Yes, you did.
パクってるよ！
This kind of rip-off is known as a homage.
パクリという名の
オマージュだよ
You just admitted it!
認めちゃってるよ！
Uwah! So cool!
うわあ カッコいい！
Anything works for you?!
何でも アリか！
えっ じゃあ
こういうのは どうですか？
Well, how about this?
（みお）眼鏡！
（男）顔の一部です
Glasses!
An intelligent and cool look that appeals to all women of any era!
（みお）
知的でクールなイメージは
いつの時代も女性の憧れ
（桜井）ああ 眼鏡ですねえ
（みお）え？
Glasses, huh?
Is his eyesight bad?
目が悪いんですか？
He should just wear contacts.
コンタクトにすれば いいものを
These two just don't get it!
（みお）こいつら
まるで分かってなーい！
Then I'll do... this!
（祐子）
じゃあ私なんか こうだもん！
They're underneath his ears!
（みお）耳の下で止めてる！
Anyhow, this is a rip-off too!
…てか これもパクりでしょ！
（祐子）
チッチッチッ　サングラスです
Tsk, tsk, tsk... they're sunglasses.
Uwah! So cool.
うわあ カッコいい
You're okay with it?!
さじ加減か！
Then... how about this?
じゃあ これで どう？
（みお）執事！
A butler!
From picking you up to serving you tea... you'll feel like a real lady.
お出迎えから紅茶サービスまで
気分は もう令嬢
Feel the magic of Darjeeling!
ダージリンの魔力を受けよ！
ああ また眼鏡
すみません よく分からなくて
Glasses again?
I'm sorry, I don't really get it.
（祐子）
フフッ　コンタクトの忠告も
聞かずに プッ ククク
She didn't listen to my advice about contacts...
（みお）グハアッ
Mio-chan, you don't get it, do you?
みおちゃんは分かってないなあ
あのねえ 本当に
カッコいいっていうのはねえ
You see, what's really cool is...
サラサラサラ こういうこと！
...this!
（みお）
ギャハー！ 浮いてる！
It's floating!
No, hold on... This... It's running?!
いや ちょっと待ってこれ
走ってんの？
Uwah! It looks so fast and cool!
うわあ 速そうでカッコいいなあ
（みお）ウソこけ！
カッコいいっていうのは…
I can't believe this!
What cool is...
カッコいいっていうのは…
（みお）
Rationally speaking...
常識的に… 常識的に考えて…
If you think about it rationally...
カッコいいっていうのは！
Cool is...
フンッ
...this, right?
（みお）こういうことでしょうが！
（男）やあ！
Oh no...
しまったああ…
Just kidding!
（みお）なーんちゃって！
アハハッ つってっ！
In front of the 1-Q lectern
Naganohara Mio:
Sunk
Word Of The Day
I drew this while listening to jazz music.
The Next Day
Morning!
（祐子）おはよう
Ah! Sensei, good morning!
あっ 先生
おはようございます
Who are you calling sensei?!
誰が先生だ！
Well then, I'll hand out this morning's mini-test,
（桜井）
では 朝の豆テスト配りますので
渡してください
so please pass them around.
I'm done for...
（みお）ああ まいった
I wanted to keep secret the fact that I draw.
絵 描いてるのは ないしょに
しとこうと思ってたんだけど
I can't believe I drew a picture like that...
まさか あんな絵
描いちゃうとは
English
Anyway, even though I lost control, only going to that level was a blessing amongst all the misfortune.
でも まあ
暴走してたにも かかわらず―
あのレベルで とどまれたのは
不幸中の幸いだよね
ギリギリ よしと
するしかないでしょ
It was pretty close.
Yukko's going to tease me for two or three days though...
でも ２～３日は ゆっこに
からかわれるんだろうなあ
No, no!
ダメダメ
割り切って 前向きに
I have to keep my chin up and move forward.
（男）やあ！
Mio-sensei, hurry up.
（祐子）みお先生　早く
Um... begin!
えーと　始めっ！
Mio-sensei!
（祐子）みお先生～！
Pleased to meet you.
I'm onomatopoeia!
You can't help but say "Cock-a-doodle-do" in Japanese even though it's not Japanese.
Narration:     Koyama Rikiya
The next Nichijou is the sixth. Look forward to it.
（オノマトペ）
キュイーン シャッ タタタッ
やあ 初めてだねえ
オノマトペだよ
クック ドゥー ドゥルドゥーは
口にしたくなる日本語だよな
日本語じゃないが
次回は「日常」の
６話だ　お楽しみに